Guide to the Alfred E. Edgcomb Papers, 1906-1983 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Alfred E. Edgcomb papers 1906-1983 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Edgcomb, Alfred E., 1867-1933.
19.2 Linear Feet Approximately 14,000 Items
Businessman active in the lumber industry.
Collection contains correspondence, legal and financial papers, printed materials, photographs, and other materials from lumber businesses beginning before 1910, especially in East Tennessee and in the Philippine Islands with headquarters in Philadelphia, Pa. The Insular Lumber Co., Negros Island, P.I., produced mahogany. Also present in the collection are personal and family papers, including numerous photographs.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research but portions of it are unprocessed and unarranged.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Alfred E. Edgcomb Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in December 1980 and 1986.
Collection Overview
Collection contains personal and business correspondence, legal and financial papers, printed materials, photographs, and other materials from lumber businesses beginning before 1910, especially in East Tennessee and in the Philippine Islands with headquarters in Philadelphia, Pa. The Insular Lumber Co., Negros Island, P.I., produced mahogany. Also present in the collection are personal and family papers, including numerous photographs and letters to the Edgcombs from friends.
Much of the collection is unprocessed and may need further processing; please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Edgcomb, Alfred E., 1867-1933
Edgcomb family
Insular Lumber Company
Lumber trade -- United States
Lumbering -- Tennessee
Lumbering -- Philippines
Lumber trade -- Records
Lumber trade -- History -- 19th century
Lumber trade -- History -- 20th century
Lumber trade -- Management
Industries -- Tennessee
United States -- Commerce -- Philippines
Philippines -- Commerce -- United States
Photographs
Contents of Collection
- Business and Financial Records, 1906-1968, (26 boxes)
  - 1922-1923 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Yokohama, Japan
  - Government of the Philippines, Department of Agriculture and National Resources correspondence
  - 1914-1919 (Box 2)
  - Bank information
  - 1914-1917 (Box 3)
  - 1908-1923 (Box 4)
  - Insular Lumber Co.: monthly financial statements, 1908-1915 (Box 5)
  - Financial correspondence and stockholders, 1906-1913
  - Fassett Lumber Co.: monthly statements, shipments, earnings, and correspondence, 1916-1923
  - 1906-1941 (Box 6)
  - Emberville Timber Co., S.S. Boveric Co., and Yadkin Lumber Co.
  - 1936-1938 (Box 7)
  - Emberville Timber Co., stockholders
  - John A. Hunter Hardwood Corporation
  - 1907-1915 (Box 8)
  - 1909-1937 (Box 9)
  - 1907-1923 (Box 10)
  - 1938 (Box 11)
  - 1908-1915 (Box 12)
  - 1911-1922 (Box 13)
  - 1939-1961 (Box 14)
  - 1914-1923 (Box 15)
  - Financial statements, 1907-1922 (Box 16)
  - 1912-1914 (Box 17)
  - Business correspondence (Box 18)
  - 1929-1940 (Box 19)
  - 1939-1961 (Box 20)
  - 1938-1968 (Box 21)
  - 1908-1922 (Box 22)
  - Stocks and market evaluations, 1937-1958 (Box 25)
  - Business materials (Box 26)
  - Property blueprints
  - Maps
  - Business correspondence copies (Box 31-32)
- Additional Personal Materials, 1930s-1950s, 1983 and undated, (8 boxes)
  Correspondence to Ruth and Alfred Edgcomb, photographs, clippings, and other materials. Most of the correpondence is still in envelopes. All materials in this addition are unprocessed and may need further processing. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.
  - Clippings (Box 23)
  - Photographs
  - Photographs (Box 24)
  - Personal correspondence
  - Photographs (Box 27-29)
  - Photographs (Box 30)
  - Miscellaneous
  - Correspondence and other materials, 1938-1959, 1983, (1.5 linear feet) (Box 33)
    Many Christmas cards from the 1930s-1950s are present, along with many personal letters to Ruth and Alfred Edgcomb. Also includes a deed, some photographs, and several issues of the Philadelphia weekly entertainment newspaper, 1980s.
  - Correspondence and cards, 1930s and 1940s, (1.5 linear feet) (Box 34)
    Includes hundreds of pieces of correspondence, including a small portion housed in small box, sent to Ruth Evelyn Blackwell before she married Alfred Edgcomb.